<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Adam Hearn</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Memorandum to Betsy Devos</title>
      <link>/post/for_prof_memo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/for_prof_memo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;memorandum&#34;&gt;MEMORANDUM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To:&lt;/strong&gt; Betsy Devos, US Secretary of Education&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From:&lt;/strong&gt; Adam Hearn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; February 22, 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subject:&lt;/strong&gt; Recommendation for Stricter Quality Control of For-Profit Institutions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recommendation&#34;&gt;Recommendation:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend that the Department of Education apply stricter quality control standards on for-profit colleges and universities. Students who attend these institutions are assured compelling employment post-graduation upon enrollment, but rarely are these promises realized. This leaky pipeline of at-risk students from the moment they step on campus (or boot up their computer, in the age of technology-driven education) to their nearly inevitable drop-out is explicitly due to the lack of governance from the Department of Education in this sector. With stricter accreditation standards and government regulation of these businesses, we can increase student attainment and postsecondary success, especially among those in traditionally underrepresented groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who attend for-profit institutions are not your typical, wide-eyed first-year college students. Instead, these students are disproportionately older, African-American, single parents.[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftn1&#34;&gt;1]&lt;/a&gt; Frankly, your administration exploits these students to the point where they are more likely to drop out and default on their loans, leaving many of these students in a position where they would have been better off not going to college at all.[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftn2&#34;&gt;2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students are attracted to these for-profit institutions due to easy enrollment and help to find financial aid. However, many of these students are disappointed with the poor quality of education they receive.[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftn3&#34;&gt;3]&lt;/a&gt; Post-graduation, this subsequently leads to troubles finding employment and unsustainable levels of debt. For-profit institutions account for roughly 22% of all postsecondary borrowers, yet these students comprise approximately 33% of all loan defaults.[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftn4&#34;&gt;4]&lt;/a&gt; These numbers suggest that the for-profit sector primarily drives the ongoing student-loan crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policies (or lack thereof) set forth by the Department of Education concerning for-profit education exacerbate many of the issues in this sector of postsecondary education, disproportionately affecting minority groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;key-proposals-for-stricter-quality-control-of-for-profit-institutions&#34;&gt;Key Proposals for Stricter Quality Control of For-Profit Institutions:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Apply     stricter standards for accreditation agencies.&lt;/em&gt; The accreditation standards put forth by the     Accrediting Council for Independent Colleges and Schools (ACICS) and other     national accrediting agencies are far too lenient. Currently, ACICS claims     that for-profit institutions are required to report a retention rate of at     least 75%.[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftn5&#34;&gt;5]&lt;/a&gt; Changing these accreditation standards to include     student outcomes (e.g., graduation rates and average debt accumulation)     would increase postsecondary student success. I understand this     administration has restored the accreditation powers of ACICS after losing     authority under the Obama administration. Still, I recommend that the     Department of Education work alongside this agency and other national     accreditors to amend their current accreditation policies to reflect     student outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mandate for-profit institutions to publish attainment and default rates.&lt;/em&gt; By requiring for-profit colleges to publish attainment     outcomes and default rates, students would be more aware of the type of     education in this sector. In doing so, for-profit institutions would     either be (a) pushed to improve their practices further, or (b) forced out     of business. This policy would increase student outcomes while maintaining     for-profit competition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Improve     information sharing on postsecondary options to prospective students.&lt;/em&gt; Students who attend for-profit institutions are more     likely to default on their loans than students who attend non-profit or     public colleges and universities.[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftn6&#34;&gt;6]&lt;/a&gt;     This behavior is likely due to a     lack of information regarding federal loans given to prospective students     before enrollment. By providing more information on postsecondary access     to prospective students through brochures at public schools, prisons, and     VA groups, students will be more aware of their postsecondary options and     financial aid obligations before enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions-and-politics&#34;&gt;Conclusions and Politics:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure these recommendations land with your administration, I want to stress the importance of aligning higher education with the needs of the economy. Because of their high tuitions and needy students, for-profit institutions consume a large amount of federal aid with minimal returns to the students or the nation’s workforce.[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftn7&#34;&gt;7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Student outcomes following enrollment at for-profit institutions are far inferior to those of non-profit or public colleges or universities, primarily due to the lack of regulation of this industry. To guarantee that the future workforce meets the needs of the economy, the quality of education received at the for-profit sector of postsecondary education needs to be on-par with its non-profit and public counterparts. These outcomes can be achieved by stricter accreditation standards while maintaining similar standards for enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The for-profit education industry exploits students of all backgrounds, including high-school drop-outs, single parents, and veterans. Your policies and actions regarding for-profit education have failed to recognize these groups and their career goals. As Secretary of Education, you should ensure that these underrepresented groups have little barriers to pursuing a quality postsecondary education with worthwhile outcomes and minimal debt. With these outcomes in mind, I hope that these recommendations and policies can gain traction under this administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftnref1&#34;&gt;1]&lt;/a&gt; Center for Analysis of Postsecondary Education and Employment. “For Profit Colleges by the Numbers.” February, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftnref2&#34;&gt;2]&lt;/a&gt; Cellini, Stephanie &amp;amp; Turner, Nicholas. (2018). “Gainfully Employed? Assessing the Employment and Earnings of For-Profit College Students Using Administrative Data.” Journal of Human Resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftnref3&#34;&gt;3]&lt;/a&gt; The Brookings Institute. “The Failings of Online For-Profit Colleges: Findings from Student Borrower Focus Groups.” March, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftnref4&#34;&gt;4]&lt;/a&gt; U.S. Department of Education, “Official Three-Year Cohort Default Rates for Postsecondary Schools.”  September 23, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftnref5&#34;&gt;5]&lt;/a&gt; Accrediting Council for Independent Colleges and Schools. “Accreditation Criteria: Policies, Procedures, and Standards.” September, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftnref6&#34;&gt;6]&lt;/a&gt; Jordan Scott-Clayton, “The Looming Student Loan Default Crisis is Worse Than We Thought.” The Brookings Institute, January 11, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftnref7&#34;&gt;7]&lt;/a&gt; United States Senate Health, Education, Labor and Pensions Committee. “For Profit Higher Education: The Failure to Safeguard the Federal Investment and Ensure Student Success.” July 30, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jesus is King: A departure from Kanye&#39;s recent projects or a return to his roots?</title>
      <link>/post/jik/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/jik/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a work in progress.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
